

Mark Howard

Senior Clinical Hypnotherapist, Mental Health Educator and Mental Health Nurse

Health City, Davenport House, 16 Pepper Street, Canary Wharf, London E14 9RP. Tel: 0333 800 3006, 0333 789 0012. Email: info@healthcity.org.uk/ Website: https://healthcity.org.uk/

I am a registered Clinical Hypnotherapist, and is also a registered mental health nurse, qualifying in 1988. I have practiced as a Hypnotherapist since 2002, having trained at the London College of Clinical Hypnosis, which is one of the leading training centres in the UK.

As a nurse, I worked for most of my clinical career as a community mental health nurse, and a clinical nurse leader, which involved supervising mental health nurse colleagues, offering clinical and care advice and guidance to other disciplines; and also spent time in an Accident and Emergency Department (A & E) training staff in working with and supporting people attending A & E with mental health needs.

I worked as a senior lecturer at a London University from 2003 to 2015, teaching health and social care. The clinical and academic roles have complemented each other, and have enhanced my work in different ways.

Similarly, my background as a mental health practitioner has supported my work as a hypnotherapist, and enables me to apply a wider perspective to the broad range of conditions that I work with. The following are among the many conditions and enhancements I have worked with:

Conditions and enhancements I have worked with:

Anxiety related disorders; panic symptoms; phobias; fear of flying; digestive system problems e.g. IBS, ulcerative colitis; weight loss; smoking cessation; performance enhancement (work, sports performance etc.).

Professional bodies:

- British Society of Clinical Hypnosis
- Nursing and Midwifery Council (NMC)
- BA Mental Health Nursing, Post-Graduate Certificate in Education, Health Professionals and MA Advanced Nursing Practice.

I trained as a mental health nurse in the 1980s and since around 1989 have developed an interest in service user perspectives, user involvement, and the lived experience - and principles of recovery, which I have incorporated in my practice, in research and in my teaching role.

I worked in community mental health services in and around East London for 14 years before taking up a full time position as a senior lecturer at London South Bank University where I worked for 12 years until March 2015.

I trained as a Hypnotherapist at the London College of Clinical Hypnosis between 2001 and 2003, and have practiced since. I have treated a range of conditions/habits etc; and with some success. My experience as a mental health nurse has helped to enhance my hypnotherapy practice in a number of ways; and offers an important dimension that would otherwise be missing from the way I work.

Despite electing to take redundancy from my education role, I hope to continue pursuing scholarly activity, and to write on the subject of lived experience, in collaboration with former colleagues. I am also preparing an article on hypnotherapy in the NHS context.

I have been working on my first novel for a very long time, owing to other distractions, but very close to the finish line now. I have plot lines for a further 4-5 novels, involving psychological dramas, and humour in a couple of cases; as well as a book of short stories (of the supernatural genre).

EXPERIENCE

Catalyst Therapy and Training Company Ltd.

March 2006 – Present (9 years 7 months) Havering, Essex.

A small company with a Hypnotherapist and a Cognitive Behavioural Therapist. On occasion a combined treatment approach is offered, and generally to positive effect.

London South Bank University

February 2003 – March 2015 (12 years 2 months) London, United Kingdom. I worked as a senior lecturer, teaching mental health practice, recovery, and the social context; additionally I taught social sciences and health politics. For about 10 years I also fulfilled the role of admissions tutor, recruiting students onto the preregistration nursing programme.

The position also included involvement with a local mental health Trust, visiting students in placement areas, and connecting with Trust colleagues, as well as involvement with audit processes.

For most of my 12 years at the university I worked closely with people who had used services, and whom worked as visiting lecturers, contributing to the programmes of learning, student recruitment and curriculum development; as well as research involvement in some cases. More recently I have been involved in engaging carers in the various activities.

EDUCATION

University of Essex

Master's Degree, Advanced Nursing Practice, Distinction 1998 – 2001

University of Greenwich

Post-Graduate Certificate in Education, Health Professionals 1997 – 1999

University of Greenwich

Bachelor's Degree, Mental Health Nursing, 2:2 1992 – 1995